Sofia Alere

Software Engineer

PROFILE

Professional Software Engineer located in Chicago with expertise in Node.js and Ruby ecosystems. I bring a strong commitment to organization and effective communication to each project in which I am involved. My most recent accomplishment includes the development of Sundial, a sophisticated cron job monitoring and management system.

SKILLS

Tools & Databases

Git/Github, SQLite, PostgreSQL, Linux, Bash, HTTP, Postman, BCrypt, RSpec, NGINX, Redis, MongoDB, Docker

Infrastructure

Digital Ocean, Render, Fly.io, Virtual Private Cloud, Heroku, AWS (EC2)

Languages & Runtimes

Javascript (ES6+), Ruby, Golang, SQL, HTML/CSS, Node.js

Libraries, Frameworks, Testing Ruby on Rails, Express, Sinatra, React/Redux, JQuery, Handlebars, SOAP, REST,

WebSockets, SSE, Jest, RSpec

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2023 – present

Software Engineer & Co-Creator, Sundial

Sundial is an open-source cron job monitoring and management system that provides job execution data and alerts, centralized error logs, and the ability to perform CRUD operations on jobs in crontabs across multiple nodes.

- Developed a suite of command-line scripts that provides users a simple integration of Sundial to their existing cron jobs. (Node.js, Javascript)
- Transformed central service set up from a 10-step+ to a 2-step process by containerizing server code. (Docker)
- Eliminated all installation dependencies on target nodes by packaging scripts into executable binaries using the 'pkg' library
- Implemented a RESTful API facilitating app component communication and persistence of cron job execution information. (Node.is, Express)
- Decoupled complex logic required to react to non-events from database entities utilizing Task Queues. (PostgreSQL)
- Constructed a responsive dashboard that provides real-time data. (React, Material UI, SSE's)
- Ensured availability by using **systemd's unit files** to daemonize the **HTTP Express** server responsible for allowing communication from the service to a node's crontab.
- Designed load tests to determine Sundial's performance under several conditions, observing a 0% failure rate up to 200 concurrent monitored jobs. (Grafana k6)
- Increased security on network connected multi-node set ups through requiring JWT Tokens and API Keys.
- Provided an alternate, more secure set up with instructions on how to deploy Sundial on Digital Ocean VPCs.
- Authored Sundial's comprehensive technical case study ...
- Collaborated remotely with a team of four engineers across three time zones, utilizing Agile workflow practices such as daily standups and pair programming. (Github, Slack, Trello)

2021 - 2023

Software Engineer, Self Employed

Developed freelance and open-source projects.

Shopify Southern Marsh Promotion:

- Identified and debugged errors in promotional logic in a **Shopify** backend.
- Enhanced resilience of codebase segment through re-factoring it in an **Object-Oriented Programming** (OOP) paradigm. (**Ruby**)

Inquiry Hub:

- Developed an application that aids in debugging web-hooks by receiving and displaying them in real-time. (React, Express, NGINX, Digital Ocean, PM2)
- Enhanced scalability by separating relational data and variable request body data to an RDBSM and a noSQL DB. (PostgreSQL, MongoDB)

2017 - 2021

Owner & Professional Yachting Contractor, Sea Nemo

Orchestrated excellent service on luxury yachts as a part of multiple skilled teams.

- Fostered a collaborative and positive work environment through developing strong connections with other team-members and guests.
- Revamped training protocols and personally mentored new staff with a focus on continuous professional development.

EDUCATION

2021 – 2023 **Launch School**

Multi-year foundations focused software engineering program where I studied the fundamentals of backend and frontend programming, database design, networking, and data driven systems design.

VOLUNTEERING

2023 –

We All Code, Coding Mentor

present Mentor kids in a variety of technologies ranging from drawing using **Javascript** to robotics using **Python**. The program is focused on inspiring people from all backgrounds to pursue STEM.